Finding aid to the Margaret Sanger Research Bureau records SSC.MS.00320
Sophia Smith Collection
- SERIES V. BOOKS, 1901-1951
  This series contains 59 titles including Margaret Sanger's Pivot of Civilization, Women and the New Race, Happiness in Marriage, and My Fight for Birth Control; seven volumes of Havelock Ellis' Studies in the Psychology of Sex; five titles by Marie Stopes as well as a biography of Stopes by Maude Alymner; and the Birth Control Congressional Hearings (1931-34).
  - Birth Control Congressional Hearings, 1931-1934 (Box 14)
  - Blacker, C.P., Birth Control and the State: A Plea and a Forecast, 1926 (Box 14)
  - Breckinridge, Sophonisba P., Marriage and the Civic Rights of Women, Separate Domicile and Independent Citizenship, 1931 (Box 14)
  - Bucke, Richard Maurice, Cosmic Consciousness: A Study In the Evolution of the Human Mind, 1901 (Box 14)
  - Carr, Norman, Birth Control in Marriage, 1931 (Box 14)
  - Carson, William E., The Marriage Revolt: A Study of Marriage and Divorce, 1915 (Box 14)
  - Chachuat, Maurice, Le Mouvement du "Birth Control" dans les Pays Anglo Saxons, 1934 (Box 14)
  - Clark, Le Mon, The Vaginal Diaphragm, Its Fitting and Use in Contraceptive Technique, 1939 (Box 14)
  - Cooper, James F., Technique of Contraception: The Principles and Practice of Anti-conceptional Methods, 1928 (Box 14)
  - Cox, Gladys M., Clinical Contraception, 1937 (Box 14)
  - Devilbiss, Lydia Allen, Birth Control, What Is It?, 1923 (Box 14)
  - Drysdale, Bessie Ingman, Labour Troubles and Birth Control, 1920 (Box 16)
  - Drysdale, C.V., et al, Small or Large Families: Birth Control From the Moral, Racial, and Eugenic Standpoint, 1917 (Box 14)
  - Ellis, Havelock, Studies in the Psychology of Sex 7v., 1901-28 (Box 15)
  - Fielding, Michael, ed., Birth Control in Asia: A Report of a Conference Held at the London School of Hygiene & Tropical Medicine, November 24-25, 1933 (1935) (Box 15)
  - Himes, Norman E., A Guide to Birth Control Literature, 1931 (Box 18)
  - ______________, Medical History of Contraception, 1936 (Box 15)
  - ______________, Praktische Methoden der Geburtenregelung, 1949 (Box 15)
  - Hodann, Max, Sexualelend und Sexualberatung, 1928 (Box 17)
  - Horder, Sir Thomas, The Cost of English Morals, 1931 (Box 14)
  - Irwin, Rita, and Clementina Paolone, Practical Birth Control, 1937 (Box 17)
  - Key, Ellen, The Century of the Child, 1909 (Box 17)
  - Knopf, S. Adolphus, The Medical, Social, Economic, Moral and Religious Aspects of Birth Control, 1926 (Box 16)
  - _______________, Various Aspects of Birth Control. (1928) (2c) (Box 16)
  - Lenz, J., The Rise and Fall of the Second International, 1932 (Box 17)
  - Lutz, Alma, Created Equal: A Biography of Elizabeth Cady Stanton, 1815-1902 (1940)
  - Maude, Alymer, The Authorized Life of Marie C. Stopes, 1924 (Box 17)
  - Meyer, Adolf, Birth Control Facts and Responsibilities, 1925 (Box 17)
  - Pancoast, Elinor, and Anne E. Lincoln, Incorrigible Idealist: Robert Dale Owen in America, 1940 (Box 17)
  - Palmer, Rachel Lynn, and Sarah K. Greenberg, Facts and Frauds in Woman's Hygiene, 1936 (Box 17)
  - Place, Francis, Illustrations and Proofs of the Principle of Population, 1930 (Box 16)
  - Raina, Lt. Cl. B.L., Family Planning, Why? When? and How?, 1951 (Box 16)
  - Raleigh, A.S., Woman and Super-Woman, 1916 (Box 17)
  - Robinson, William J., Birth Control or The Limitation of Offspring by Prevention of Conception, 1928 (Box 17)
  - Rout, Ettie A., The Morality of Birth Control, 1925 (Box 14)
  - Sanger, Margaret, and Hannah Stone, ed., The Practice of Contraception: An International Symposium and Survey, 1931 (Box 16)
  - Sanger, Margaret, Die Neue Mutterschaft, 1927 (Box 17)
  - ______________, Happiness in Marriage, 1926 (Box 16)
  - ______________, My Fight For Birth Control, 1931 (Box 16)
  - ______________, The Pivot of Civilization, 1922 (Box 17)
  - ______________, Woman and the New Race, 1920 (Box 17)
  - Stopes, Marie Carmichael, Contraception Its Theory, History and Practice, 1931 (Box 16)
  - _____________________, Enduring Passion, 1929 (Box 17)
  - _____________________, The Human Body, 1926 (Box 17)
  - _____________________, Mother England, A Contemporary History, 1929 (Box 14)
  - _____________________, Wise Parenthood, 1922 (Box 17)
  - Sutherland, Halliday G., Birth Control, 1922 (Box 18)
  - Swedenborg, Emanuel, Delights of Wisdom Concerning Conjugal Love: After Which Follow Pleasures of Insanity Concerning Scortatory Love, 1923 (Box 18)
  - Telling, W.H. Maxwell, et al, Medical Help on Birth Control, 1928 (Box 18)
  - Vaughan Father Bernard, The Menace of the Empty Cradle, 1917 (Box 18)
  - Westermarck, Edward, The History of Human Marriage, 1903 (Box 16)
  - Whitney, Leon F., Sex and Birth Control, 1932 (Box 18)
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  - 194 Glass slides and two films used by Norman Hines for birth control lectures, 1930s (Box 12, Box 13)
- Aquiles Sobrero collection of additional items regarding the Margaret Sanger Research Bureau, approximately 1965-1980; 2017-S-0068; Sobrero, Adela M.; Sobrero, Ral; 1.25 linear feet (1 oversize box, 1/2 document box, 2 small card files)
  Appraisal
  Aquiles Sobrero was the last director of the Margaret Sanger Research Bureau; these photographs and materials document the work of the bureau.
  A collection that includes photographs, informational pamphlets, correspondence, diplomas, awards, office materials, contact information, and research card files pertaining to the practice of Dr. Aquiles Sobrero.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  This small accession of additional materials from was donated by Adela and Ral Sobrero in 2017.
  Sobrero, Adela M.; Sobrero, Ral
  - Diplomas and oversize photographs, 1953-1969 (Box 1)
  - Photographs, honors, diplomas, and office papers, 1960-1980 (Box 2)
  - Research card file, 1950-1965 (Box 3)
  - Contact Rolodex, approximately 1960-1970 (Box 4)